Guide to the Alfred Bettman papers, 1910-1945
Bettman, Alfred papers, 1910-1945
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Alfred Bettman Papers, 1910-1945
2774
Alfred Bettman, 1873-1945.
33 reels, 1 folder
Microfilm reels and a photocopy of a pamphlet.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Microfilmed papers include correspondence, memoranda, drafts, lectures, clippings, minutes, articles, pamphlets, programs, budgets, reports, briefs, regulations, and records of conferences and committees pertaining to various planning agencies and projects. Also includes a photocopied "Draft of an Act for Urban Development and Redevelopment," by Alfred Bettman, 1943.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Alfred Bettman was a city planner.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Microfilmed papers include correspondence, memoranda, drafts, lectures, clippings, minutes, articles, pamphlets, programs, budgets, reports, briefs, regulations, and records of conferences and committees pertaining to the American Bar Association, American City Planning Institute, American Institute of Planners, American Society of Planning Officials, Better Housing Authority, Cincinnati City Planning Commission, Cincinnati Metropolitan Housing Authority, Federal Reserve, Maryland National Park and Planning Commission, National Capital Park and Planning Commission, National Resources Planning Board, Regional Planning Commission of Hamilton County, Ohio, Resettlement Administration, Tennessee Valley Authority, and the U.S. Department of Commerce Advisory Committee on Planning and Zoning. Material relates primarily to zoning, housing, and city planning in Alabama, Illinois, Indiana, Kentucky, Puerto Rico, Tennessee, West Virginia, and Wisconsin. Also includes a photocopied "Draft of an Act for Urban Development and Redevelopment," by Alfred Bettman, 1943.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bettman, Alfred, 1873-1945.; American Bar Association.; American Institute of Planners.; Better Housing Authority (Cincinnati, Ohio); Cincinnati (Ohio). City Planning Commission.; Cincinnati (Ohio). Metropolitan Housing Authority.; Maryland. National Park and Planning Commission.; Regional Planning Commission (Hamilton Co., Ohio); Tennessee Valley Authority.; United States. Federal Reserve.; United States. National Capital Park and Planning Commission.; United States. National Resources Planning Board.; United States. Resettlement Administration.; United States. Dept. of Commerce. Advisory Committee on Planning and Zoning.
Subjects:
City planning--Alabama.; City planning--Illinois.; City planning--Indiana.; City planning--Kentucky.; City planning--Puerto Rico.; City planning--Tennessee.; City planning--West Virginia.; City planning--Wisconsin.; City planning and redevelopment law.; Housing.; Regional planning.; Zoning.; Cincinnati (Ohio)--City planning.; City planners.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Available Copies:
Originals held by the University of Cincinnati.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Public activities
  - Cincinnati City Planning Commission
    - Correspondence, 1919-1944 (Reel 1-3)
    - Proceedings of the Commission, 1927-1928 (Reel 3)
    - Proceedings of the Commission, 1929 (Reel 3)
    - Proceedings of the Commission, 1936-1944 (Reel 3)
    - Calendars of the Commission meetings, 1927-1940 (Reel 3)
    - Budgets for Commission and related correspondence, 1937-1944 (Reel 3)
    - United City Planning Committee, ca. 1922-1926 (Reel 3)
    - Master Plan, ca. 1942-1944 (Reel 3)
    - City Bond and improvement program, ca. 1926-1945 (Reel 3)
    - Technical Advisory Corp. and the City Plan (Preliminary Report - 1922 and final scheme - 1925 ) (Reel 3-4)
    - Zoning Board of Appeals
      - Correspondence, 1926-1931 (Reel 4)
      - Annual Reports, 1926-1938 (Reel 4)
    - Zoning Regulations, Building Codes, etc.
      - Cincinnati City Planning reports (Reel 4)
      - Drafts, ca. 1929-1932 (Reel 4)
    - Miscellaneous Zoning manuscripts (Reel 5)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Price Hill area (Reel 5)
      - Flood control (Reel 5)
      - Misc. reports, 1932-1937 (Reel 5)
      - Undated misc. (Reel 5)
      - Newspaper clippings (Reel 5)
    - Bureau of Municipal Research (Governmental Research) (Reel 5)
  - Regional Planning Commission of Hamilton County, Ohio
    - Correspondence, Mar. 19, 1928-Dec. 4, 1941 (Reel 5)
    - Sub-division regulations, 1937-1941 (Reel 6)
    - Zoning, 1936-1941 (Reel 6)
    - Drafts, ca. 1935-1941 (Reel 6)
    - Misc. pamphlets (Reel 6)
    - Minutes of Commission, 1929-1941 (Reel 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel 6)
  - National Resources Planning Board
    - National Resources Board--correspondence 1933-May 1935 (Reel 6-7)
    - National Resources Commission
      - Correspondence, June-Oct. 1935 (Reel 7)
      - Correspondence, Nov. 1935-Feb. 1936 (Reel 7)
      - Correspondence, Mar.-Dec. 1936 (Reel 7-8)
      - Correspondence, Feb.-Dec. 1937 (Reel 8)
      - Correspondence, Jan.-Apr. 1938 (Reel 8-9)
      - Correspondence, May-Dec. 1938 (Reel 9)
      - Correspondence, Jan. 1938-May 1939 (Reel 10)
    - Miscellaneous National Resources Commission
      - Stream Pollution Compact Commission, flood control, etc. (Reel 10)
      - Drainage basin--Scioto, Ohio (Reel 10)
      - B-56 bulletin (Reel 11)
      - Roadside development (Reel 11)
      - Cutover reports (Reel 11)
      - State planning--Indiana and Wisconsin (Reel 11)
      - State planning--Illinois and W. Virginia (Reel 11)
      - State planning--Tennessee and Kentucky (Reel 11)
      - State planning boards--General (Reel 11)
      - Travelling expenses and correpondence (Reel 11-12)
      - Misc. bulletins, pamphlets, and reports (Reel 12)
    - National Resources Planning Board
      - General correspondence, July 1939-1944 (Reel 12)
      - General travelling expenses, etc. (Reel 12-13)
      - Puerto Rico planning
        - Correspondence, 1941-1944 (Reel 13)
        - Travel correspondence and expenses, 1941 (Reel 13)
        - Memos to Gov. Tugwell, 1941-1942 (Reel 13)
        - Articles, etc. re: Gov. Tugwell (Reel 13)
        - Martinez memoes (Reel 13)
        - Drafts of stages of zoning bill, 1941 (Reel 13)
        - Misc. drafts (Reel 14)
- Series II. Civic activities
  - Advisory Committee on Planning and Zonings of U.D. Dept. of Commerce
    - Papers, ca. 1929-1937 (Reel 14)
  - American City Planning Institute
    - Correspondence, 1923-1940 (Reel 14)
    - Misc. reports (zoning plans) (Reel 14)
  - American Institute of Planners
    - Correspondence, 1935-1944 (Reel 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel 14)
  - American Society of Planning Officers
    - Correspondence, 1934-1938 (Reel 14-15)
    - Correspondence, 1939-1945 (Reel 15)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Reports--Minutes of Society, 1935-1936 (Reel 15)
      - Redevelopment Committee--drafts and reports (Reel 15)
      - Redevelopment Committee--pamphlets and misc. reports (Reel 15)
      - Redevelopment Bill--misc. drafts (Reel 16)
  - National Conference on City Planning
    - Correspondence, 1919-1920, Program for Conference, 1920 (Reel 16)
    - Reorganization Committee, 1933-1935 (Reel 16)
    - Amalgamation with A.C.P.I., ca. 1934-1935 (Reel 16)
    - Program and Expense Budget for 1935 Conference (Reel 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Reel 17)
  - National Municipal League Committee on Municipal Charter
    - Correspondence, 1929-1944 (Reel 17)
    - Misc. drafts, reports, minutes, meetings, etc. (Reel 17)
  - Ohio State Conference on City Planning
    - Correspondence, 1919-1925 (Reel 17)
    - Correspondence, 1926-1941 (Reel 18)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Programs and proceedings, 1920-1931 (Reel 18)
      - Legislative Committee reports, 1922-1925 (Reel 18)
      - Misc. drafts of act and bills for legislative committee (Reel 18)
      - Misc. reports and pamphlets (Reel 18)
  - Ohio State Planning Board
    - County Zoning (possibly re: Ohio State Conference)
      - Correspondence, 1933-1939 (Reel 19)
      - Correspondence, 1941-1945 (Reel 19)
      - Minutes of meetings, 1934-1936 (Reel 19)
      - Misc. drafts (Reel 19)
- Series III. Professional activities
  - American Bar Association
    - Correspondence, 1928-1944 (Reel 19)
    - Reports (Reel 19)
  - Legal cases
    - City Bulletin Case, 1933 (Reel 19)
    - City of Cincinnati vs. Vester, 1930 (Reel 19)
    - City of Cincinnati vs. Wess, 1933 (Reel 19)
    - Devoll vs. Better Housing League, 1929 (Reel 19-20)
    - Eighth Street Viaduct Case, 1926-1928 (Reel 20)
    - Erdman vs. Hauser, n.d. (Reel 20)
    - Land Registration Case, 1927-1928 (Reel 20)
    - Meyer vs. Cupid Ice Cream Company, 1934 (Reel 20)
    - Pritz vs. Messer, 1924-1925 (Reel 20)
  - Maryland National Park and Planning Commission
    - Correspondence, 1927-1940 (Reel 20)
    - Correspondence, 1941-1944 (Reel 21)
    - Drafts re: formation of Commission (Reel 21)
    - Misc. litigation and legislation material (Reel 21)
    - Pritz case (Reel 21)
    - Misc. zoning drafts (Reel 21)
    - Misc. printed material (Reel 22)
  - National Capital Park and Planning Commission
    - Correspondence, 1926-1943 (Reel 22-23)
    - Correspondence, 1944-1945 (Reel 23)
    - Memos, 1936-1944 (Reel 23)
    - Reports, 1926-1944 (Reel 23)
    - Drafts re: formation of Commission (Reel 23)
    - Drafts, 1943 (Reel 23)
    - Drafts, 1944 (Reel 23)
    - Pamphlets (Reel 24)
    - Misc. notes, etc. (Reel 24)
  - Resettlement Administration
    - Papers, 1935-1940 (Reel 24)
  - State legislation in zoning, planning, etc.
    - Akron, Ohio, 1929 (Reel 24)
    - Birmingham, Alabama, 1926-1929 (Reel 24)
    - Euclid Village Case, 1923-1931 (Reel 24)
    - Lexington, Kentucky, 1929-1930 (Reel 24-25)
    - Louisville, Kentucky--building line case
      - Correspondence, 1936-1939 (Reel 25)
      - Drafts (Reel 25)
    - Missouri, 1927-1933 (Reel 25-26)
    - Princeton, New Jersey, 1928-1930 (Reel 26)
    - TVA and Tennessee State planning, 1933-1939 (Reel 26)
    - Louisville, Kentucky, Housing case, 1933-1936 (Reel 26)
  - Technical Advisory Corporation
    - Papers (Reel 26)
- Series IV. General planning information--city, state, regional planning
  - Housing
    - Better Housing League, 1931-1944 (Reel 26)
    - Cincinnati Housing Corporation, 1933-1934 (Reel 26)
    - Cincinnati Metropolitan Housing Authority, 1933-1936 (Reel 27)
    - Federal Reserve
      - Correspondence, 1936-1945 (Reel 27)
      - Drafts (Wagner and Thomas bills) (Reel 27)
      - Misc. memos, reports, drafts re: Wagner and Thomas bills (Reel 27-28)
    - Misc. housing
      - Correspondence, 1930-1943 (Reel 28)
      - Misc. reports, bills, pamphlets (Reel 28)
  - Planning
    - Planning decisions
      - Correspondence, 1929-1945 (Reel 28-29)
      - Briefs (Reel 29)
      - Rough notes and drafts (Reel 29)
      - Misc. planning (Reel 29)
    - Regional planning--general
      - Correspondence, 1927-1941 (Reel 30)
      - Misc. reports, pamphlets, articles (Reel 30)
    - Building Line Authority, 1927-1937 (Reel 30-31)
  - Roadside zoning
    - Papers, 1932-1942 (Reel 31)
  - Misc. printed pamphlets and articles
    - Papers (Reel 31-32)
- Series V. Alfred Bettman's writings
  - Lectures at Harvard and Western Reserve
    - Papers (Reel 32)
  - Misc. writings
    - Correspondence re: some articles, 1929-1944 (Reel 32)
- Series VI. Miscellaneous correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1910-1944 (Reel 33)
- Series VII. Maps and plans
  - Cincinnati City Planning Commission (Reel 33)
  - Louisville, Kentucky (Reel 33)
  - Maryland National Park and Planning Commission (Reel 33)
  - National Capital Park and Planning Commission (Reel 33)
  - Miscellaneous (Reel 33)